John A. Dahlgren Collection
John A. Dahlgren Collection
1823-1945
Dahlgren, John Adolphus Bernard, 1809-1870.
2.0 linear ft.
Papers of the U.S. naval officer, established ordnance system. Collection includes correspondence (1836-1905); 13 diaries (1834-1870); notebooks, memoranda, articles, and other papers relating to Dahlgren's naval career, including his pioneer work in naval ordnance, and the development of the Dahlgren gun. Includes a diary of his wife, Madeleine Vinton Dahlgren, and a Civil War journal of an unidentified person. Correspondence includes that of Madeleine Vinton Dahlgren, Percival Drayton, Andrew H. Foote, R.B. Forbes, R.P. Parrott, Henry Augustus Wise, and others.
148924
Biographical History
John A. Dahlgren (1809-1870) was an American naval officer and inventor of ordnance. Dahlgren, of Swedish ancestry, grew up in Philadelphia, where he showed considerable intellectual ability in the school work of his youth. His early enthusiasm led him to enter the Navy. He made several cruises, and in 1834 worked on a survey of the United States coastline. He was promoted to lieutenant and, following a short period of ill health, began ordnance duty in Washington.
That year, 1847, was the beginning of an association with the Naval Bureau of Ordnance that was to last sixteen years. Over those years Dahlgren became Chief of Ordnance and received worldwide recognition as a man of great inventive intelligence in the fields of weaponry and ammunition. He developed a number of inventions and techniques, and wrote several books on boat howitzers, percussion locks, shells and shell guns and similar subjects. Dahlgren became famous for his invention of two new guns, smoothbores which took nine and eleven inch shells. These guns, popularly called "Dahlgrens," contributed decisively to the firepower that gave naval supremacy to the Union in the Civil War.
The Civil War brought Dahlgren's naval career into prominence. He was appointed by Abraham Lincoln as Commandant of the Washington Navy Yard, an extremely important post both for ordnance and for defense of the city of Washington. Dahlgren worked in close contact with Lincoln and many of his cabinet, including Secretary of War Edwin M. Stanton, Secretary of the Treasury Salmon P. Chase, Secretary of the Navy Gideon Wells and others. Dahlgren already knew or would meet in the course of the war most of the prominent figures in the Union army and navy. He was soon promoted to captain and in 1863 to rear admiral in command of the South Atlantic Blockading Squadron. This position took him away from Washington and into the field of action. He commanded a naval assault on Charleston, an attack which because of its only partial success, provoked some criticism. He also led an expedition up the St. John's River in Florida, co-operated with Sherman in the capture of Savannah, and participated in the final occupation of Charleston. After the war, Dahlgren spent some years as commander of the South Pacific Squadron, and later returned to his old positions as Chief of Ordnance and Commandant of the Washington Navy Yard. He died in 1870.
Dahlgren married Mary Bunker in 1839, and they had seven children before her death in 1855. The most famous of these was Ulric, who rose to the rank of colonel in the Union army distinguishing himself at Fredericksburg, Chancellorsville, Second Bull Run and Gettysburg. When he died at the age of twenty-one in 1864, Ulric Dahlgren was a well-known Union war hero. Dahlgren married his second wife, Madeleine Vinton in 1865. They had three children. She wrote a biography of her husband, Memoir of John A. Dahlgren, after his death, as well as a number of other books. In her later years, Madeleine Vinton Dahlgren was a prominent figure in Washington literary circles.
A genealogical chart of the Dahlgren family appears at the end of this finding aid. This is an incomplete chart, meant only as a general guideline. The individuals represented in this collection are noted in capital lettering.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The John A. Dahlgren Papers are organized in five sections: correspondence, memorabilia, military records, writings and miscellany. The materials date from 1823 to 1945, with the bulk originating in the period 1855-1870.
Correspondence (boxes 1-2) dates from 1836 to 1905; an index to correspondents is provided at the end of this finding aid. Dahlgren corresponded with a number of men prominent in military and naval affairs and in ordnance. Most of his incoming correspondence, concentrated in the year 1855, comprises the contents of a letter book labeled "Correspondence in regard to Manufacture of the New Ordnance-- IX in and XI in guns." There are about 180 letters, which deal very largely with developments and problems in ordnance. Notable among those who wrote to Dahlgren are Silas Bent, Percival Drayton, Henry Du Pont, Andrew Hull Foote, Robert Bennet Forbes, James Harlan, Catesby Ap Roger Jones, Alfred Mordecai, Robert P. Parrot, George A. Steers, and Henry Augustus Wise.
Dahlgren's outgoing correspondence, nineteen items, dates from 1836 to 1865. Notable correspondents here include Henry Bowen Anthony, Charles Henry Davis, Andrew Hull Foote, John Parker Hale, William Nicholson Jeffers and Gideon Welles. These include a few letters of orders to Dahlgren's naval subordinates and a small number of U.S. military telegrams. Of special interest is Dahlgren's letter of February 1865 to Welles, offering his resignation from the command of the South Atlantic Blockading Squadron in the belief that General Quincy Adams Gillmore, an old personal enemy, was to take command in the Charleston area.
There is also correspondence from other members of Dahlgren's family. His second wife, Madeleine Vinton Dahlgren, his daughter Ulrica, his son Eric Dahlgren all corresponded with Charles Cowley in the later decades of the 1800's. Cowley had served under Dahlgren and was the head of the veterans' organization of the South Atlantic Blockading Squadron. Their correspondence was chiefly concerned with securing a monument and other honors to Dahlgren after his death. There is one letter written by Ulric Dahlgren in his childhood. In addition, there is a small amount of Charles Cowley's own correspondence with other veterans.
Memorabilia section (box 2), 1823-1891, contains a folder of assorted ephemera, a genealogical record of a family named Lander, some newspaper clippings and magazine separates, and one of Dahlgren's school notebooks which has a few pages of diary entries at the end. There are also two photographs of Dahlgren.
Military records (box 2) date from 1844 to 1864. These relate to Dahlgren's naval service, including orders, memoranda, a report and a book which contains shipboard regulations, procedures and mathematical tables.
Writings (boxes 2-4) date from 1829 to 1945. The writings of John A. Dahlgren himself, including thirteen volumes of his diaries and one journal, form the bulk of this section. Dahlgren's diaries, which date from 1834 to 1870, were kept with great regularity and in extensive detail. The volumes from the Civil War years are especially notable as rich sources for information on the war generally, on its naval and ordnance aspects, and on Abraham Lincoln.
In the early years of the war, before his reassignment to the Atlantic Squadron took him away from Washington, Dahlgren was quite close to Lincoln. His diaries note numerous dinners at the White House, outings with Lincoln by carriage or boat, any many meetings and conferences. There are frequent entries recording Lincoln's opinions of various generals, his interest in modern weaponry, his problems with his cabinet and Congress. Dahlgren also describes Lincoln at ease, taking breakfast in his drawers and telling stories, or cruising up the Potomac and test-firing one of the "Dahlgrens" himself. He often quotes or paraphrases Lincoln.
The diary pages contain mention of many other famous men of the Civil War, including Stanton, Chase, Wells, Sherman, McClellan, Ericsson and others whom Dahlgren knew. Even when he was not personally involved with an individual or an event, Dahlgren often wrote a well-informed account of opinion in these volumes. He wrote extensive discussions of strategy and new developments in weapons and ammunition, and occasionally he wrote about the political and social aspects of the war.
In the years preceding and following the Civil War, Dahlgren's diaries form a record of his naval assignments and ordnance work, as well as of his family and personal life. One notable entry, in October 1866, contains his copy of a letter of O. A. Brownson to Madeleine Vinton Dahlgren commenting on Dahlgren's manuscript of his book about his son, Memoir of Ulric Dahlgren. Dahlgren's single journal, the daily record of a specific activity stems from his 1829 cruise on the U.S.S. Ontario to the Mediterranean.
In addition to Dahlgren's writings, there are a few notes by Charles Cowley, apparently for a book on the Civil War, while Madeleine Vinton Dahlgren is represented by her 1861 diary and a piece of verse. There is one folder of miscellaneous fragments of writings, and one holograph draft of a book whose author is unidentified. There is also a modern biography of Admiral Dahlgren by C. Stewart Peterson, who used Dahlgren's diaries in his research.
Two folders of Miscellany (box 4) contain, among other things, several bookplates and illustrations, a map of the southern hemisphere, a few receipts, and a copy of a petition to Congress to erect a monument to Dahlgren.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence has been arranged chronologically; an index to correspondents is provided at the end of this finding aid. Memorabilia and military records are in alphabetical order by topic, type, or title. Writings are in Dahlgren's original order.
Related Material
has several other collections of Civil War material. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Military history; Civil War (U.S.); Dahlgren, John Adolphus Bernard, 1809-1870.; Dahlgren, Madeleine Vinton.; Drayton, Percival, 1812-1865.; Foote, Andrew H. (Andrew Hull), 1806-1863.; Forbes, R. B. (Robert Bennet), 1804-1889.; Parrott, R. P. (Robert Parker), 1804-1877.; Wise, Henry Augustus.; United States. Navy.; United States. Navy -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States. Navy -- Officers.; United States. Navy -- Officers -- Diaries.; Naval art and science.; Naval gunnery.; Ordnance, Naval.; United States -- History, Naval.; Correspondence.; Diaries.; Admirals.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Purchase, 1969-1971.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - [General], Undated (Box 1)
  - [General], 1836 (Box 1)
  - [General], 1847 (Box 1)
  - [General], 1850-1851 (Box 1)
  - [General], 1855 (Box 1)
  - [General], 1856-1859 (Box 1)
  - [General], 1861-1865 (Box 1)
  - [General], 1870 (Box 1)
  - 1872 (Box 1)
  - [General], 1875-1885 (Box 1)
  - [General], 1887 (Box 1)
  - [General], 1889-1899 (Box 1)
  - [General], 1900-1902 (Box 2)
  - [General], 1904-1905 (Box 2)
- Memorabilia
  - Ephemera, 1855-1891 (Box 2)
  - Genealogical Record: Lander family, ca.1862 (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings and magazine separates, 1846-1895 (Box 2)
  - Photographs (Box 2)
  - School notebook (Vol.1), 1823-1825 (Box 2)
- Military records
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Book of Rules, Procedures and Mathematical Tables (Vol. 2), 1844 (Box 2)
  - Orders and Memoranda, 1863-1864 (Box 2)
  - Report (Box 2)
- Writings
  - Miscellaneous fragments (Box 2)
  - Cowley, Charles
    - Notes on the Civil War (Box 2)
  - Dahlgren, John A.
    - Diaries
      - Fragments (Box 2)
      - (Vol. 3), 1834 (Box 2)
      - (Vol. 4), 1840 (Box 2)
      - (Vol. 5), 1842-1855 (Box 2)
      - (Vol. 6), 1854-1860 (Box 2)
      - (Vol. 7), 1860-1861 (Box 3)
      - (Vol. 8), 1861-1862 (Box 3)
      - (Vol. 9), 1862-1863 (Box 3)
      - (Vol. 10), 1863 (Box 3)
      - (Vol. 11), 1863-1864 (Box 3)
      - (Vol. 12), 1864 (Box 3)
      - (Vol. 13), 1864-1866 (Box 4)
      - (Vol. 14), 1866-1868 (Box 4)
      - (Vol. 15), 1898-1870 (Box 4)
    - Journals
      - Cruise of U.S.S. Ontario, 1829-1831 (Box 4)
  - Dahlgren, Madeleine Vinton
    - Diary (Vol. 16), 1861 (Box 4)
    - Verse, 1884 (Box 4)
  - Peterson, C. Stewart
    - Book: Admiral John A. Dahlgren, Father of U.S. Naval Ordnance, New York: Hobson (Vol. 17), circa 1945 (Box 4)
  - Unidentified
    - Book: On the Civil War, draft, chaps. 1-7. holograph (Box 4)
- Miscellany
  - Fragments (Box 4)
  - General (Box 4)
Selected index to correspondence
Key: --- indicates unknown; JAD is John A. Dahlgren
---- to ---- 1862 Jul 8
---- to JAD 1885 Apr 18
Adee, Alvey to Madeleine Vinton Dahlgren 1880 Jan 12
Adamson, J. Constantin to JAD 1855 Jun 7
Ames, Adelbert to Charles Cowley 1898 Jun 21
Ammen, Daniel to Charles Cowley 1897 Jun 1
Ammen, Daniel to JAD 1862 Aug 14
Anthony, Henry Bowen from JAD [no year] Apr 10
Archer, J.L. (?) to JAD 1855 Feb 16
Badger, O.C. to JAD 1865 Sep 20
Bell, H.H. to JAD 1855 Apr 3
Bent, Silas to JAD 1855 Oct 13
Bigelow, J. to JAD 1855 Oct 15
Bissell, George E. to Charles Cowley 1900 Jun - 1902 Jan (2 items)
Bormann to JAD 1855 Jun 7
Broun, E. to JAD 1855 Nov 9
Brown, William S. to Charles Cowley 1893 Sep 5
Burns, Rob to JAD 1855 May 28
Chauncey, John to JAD 1855 Feb 1
Clevertzmius (?), John to JAD 1855 Apr 26
Cochran, J.W. to JAD 1855 May-Jun (2 items)
Cooke, John to JAD 1855 Apr 24
Culp, E.C. to Charles Cowley 1889 Sep 13
Creighton, Capt. J. Blakeley from JAD 1864 Dec-1865 Feb (4 items)
Dahlgren, C.B. to Charles Cowley 1855 Sep - 1902 Sep (6 items)
Dahlgren, Eric B. to Charles Cowley undated (3 items)
Dahlgren, Eric B. to Madeleine Vinton Dahlgren 1891 Dec 21 (3 items)
---- from JAD undated and 1864 Aug (3 items)
Campbell, W. H. from JAD 1863 Sep 26
Davis, Charles Henry from JAD [no year] Mar 5
Dayton, A.O. from JAD 1851 May 26
Edwards, James L. from JAD 1836 May 10
Foote, Andrew Hull from JAD 1858 Dec 10
Hale, John Parker from JAD 1862 Jan 15
Harrison, Henry L. from JAD 1861 May & 1864 Feb (2 items)
Jeffers, William Nicholson from JAD 1865 Jun 24
Scott, G.H. from JAD 1865 Feb (4 items)
Weaver, A.W. from JAD 1865 Mar 8
Welles, Gideon from JAD 1865 Feb 7
Dahlgren, John A. (nephew, son of Charles G. Dahlgren) to Charles Cowley 1899 Dec 26
Dahlgren, Madeleine Vinton to Charles Cowley 1872 Feb - 1897 Nov (47 items)
Dahlgren, Madeleine Vinton to ---- undated
Dahlgren, Madeleine Vinton to Swormstedt & Poe 1859 Jun 17
Dahlgren, Ulric to Aunt Sallie and Uncle Abbott 1855 Nov 8
DeCamp, John to JAD 1855 Jan 18
Doenin, T.A. to JAD 1855 Nov 10
Drayton, Percival to JAD 1855 Jan-Nov (15 items)
Drexel, Mrs. Joseph to Charles Cowley [no year] Jun
Drexel, Lucy W. to Charles Cowley 1899 Jul 19
Du Pont, Henry to JAD 1855 Oct 11
Emilio, Luis H. to Charles Cowley 1883 Jun 2
Ferguson, J. to JAD 1855 Feb-Oct (3 items)
Foote, Andrew Hull to JAD 1855 Feb-Nov (10 items)
Forbes, Robert Bennet to JAD 1855 Feb - 1858 Feb 14
Ford, George W. to Charles Cowley 1882 Aug 3
Foster, G. John G. to JAD 1864 Jun 14
Foster, Martha P. to JAD 1864 Feb 6
Francis, Joseph to JAD 1855 Mar 8
Furlong, Wesley J. to Charles Cowley 1896 Sep 14
Gordon, George A. to Charles Cowley 1892 Aug 30
Gibbons, James (Archbishop of Baltimore) to Madeleine Vinton Dahlgren 1844 May 13
Hammersly, L.R. to JAD 1870 Jan 2
Harlan, James to JAD 1865 Mar 27
Harlan, Mrs. James to JAD 1862 Aug 10
Hendry, F. to Charles Cowley 1899 May 23
Home, F.W. to JAD 1855 Feb 19
Hunt, T.A. to JAD 1855 Oct 5
J.P.M. to JAD 1855 Feb 17
Jenkins, Thornton to JAD 1855 Feb-Jul (2 items)
Johnson, John to Charles Cowley 1899 Dec 23
Jones, Catesby Ap Rogers to JAD 1855 Sep (2 items)
Lilly, Samuel to JAD 1855 Feb 23
M.R.S. to JAD 1855 May 8
Mallory, S.R. to JAD 1855 Jan 10
Marsten, John to JAD 1855 May 7
Maryland Institute for the Promotion of the Mechanic Arts to JAD 1855 Jan
Maynadier, W. to JAD 1855 Jul 20
McCorkle, J.P. to JAD 1855 Apr-Oct (8 items)
Mission, J. to JAD 1855 Jul-Nov (4 items)
Mitchuck (?), M. to JAD 1855 Jun-Aug (2 items)
Momson, E. to JAD 1855 Apr 17
Mordecai, Alfred to JAD 1855 Jan-Apr (3 items)
Morris, C. to H. Paulding 1855 Jun 11
Munt, Leo W. to JAD 1855 Mar 16
Murphy, Thomas to JAD 1855 May 5
Newton, Isaac to JAD 1865 (2 items)
Noyes, F.G. to Charles Cowley 1900 Jan 10
O'Sullivan, J.L. to JAD 1857 Dec 17
Parker, ---- A. to JAD 1863 Jul 28
Parrott, Robert P. to JAD 1855 Mar-Nov (6 items)
Paulding, H. to JAD 1861 Apr (2 items)
Pendergast (?), G.I. to JAD 1856 Apr 27
Picard, Martyn V. to Madeleine Vinton Dahlgren undated
Pierce, Ulrica Dahlgren to Charles Cowley 1900 Jun-1905 Jan (7 items)
Pierce, Ulrica Dahlgren to Madeleine Vinton Dahlgren undated (3 items)
Porter, W.D. to JAD 1855 Nov 8
Rencill (?), L. to Charles Cowley 1900 Jun 28
Renshaw, W.B. to JAD 1855 Oct-Nov (3 items)
Richmond, William to JAD 1855 Jun 22
Riggs & Co. to Madeleine Vinton 1879 Mar 13
Riuggold, C. to JAD 1857 Apr 14
Rodman, Gilbert to JAD 1855 Sep 14
Sanford, J.P. to JAD 1855 May 1
Saltus, F.H. to Madeleine Vinton 1891 Jan 6
Schellinger, J.N. to Joseph Francis 1855 Mar 9
Schellinger, J.N. to JAD 1855 Mar 15
Screvan, John to Charles Cowley 1899 Jul 21
Sedgwick, C.B. to JAD 1864 Sep 5
Sellers, William to JAD 1855 Feb 19
Sibbern, G. to JAD 1855 Mar 31
Smith, Joseph to JAD 1847 Apr - 1855 Jan (2 items)
Smith, Truman (?) to JAD 1855 Jun 21
Snowdial (?), Yates to Charles Cowley 1881 Feb 2
Steers, George A. to JAD 1855 Mar-Apr (2 items)
Stevens, Adelaide to F.G. Noyes 1900 Jan 10
Swinnerton, S.A. to Charles Cowley 1896 Dec 11
Taylor, William Rogers to JAD 1855 Jan 1
Thatcher, H.R. to JAD 1855 Mar 23
Thomas, Lynall to JAD undated[?]
Thomas (?), V. to JAD 1855 Jul 28
Toncey, Isaac to JAD 1858 Nov 16
Turner, John Wesley to Charles Cowley 1891 Oct 21
Turner, L. to JAD 1855 Mar (23 items)
Upsham, G.P. to JAD 1847 Dec (18 items)
U.S. Secy of Navy (Clerk for) to JAD 1847 Jan (21 items)
U.S. Dept. of Treasury to JAD 1865 Nov (25 items)
Wade, W. to JAD 1855 Jul (28 items)
Walker, William to JAD 1855 Sep (28 items)
Warrington, L. to JAD 1847 Jul-1850 Nov (2 items)
Washington, P.G. to JAD 1855 Feb (18 items)
Welsh, G.P. to JAD 1855 Mar (2 items)
White, Rollin to JAD 1855 Apr (7 items)
Wise, Henry Augustus to JAD 1855 Jan-1863 (54 items)
Wright, Hendrick B. to JAD 1855 Feb (16 items)